<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The rebels looking-glasse: or, The traytors doome. Wherein is discovered the judgements of God upon the rebels and traytors in all ages: collected out of several histories both sacred &amp; profane. With a narration of this present rebellion, and of the horrid and execrable acts committed therin, and the judgements of God already observed to be saln upon the first actors and tormentors thereof. Published for the reducing of those that are already rebells, and deterring others from that sinne, / By a faithfull and loyall subject to the present king, and a lover of his country.</title>
            <author>Faithfull and loyall subject to the present King.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74084</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865057</idno>
  <idno type="VID">165093</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240907268</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R604</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E554_23</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205776</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865057</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99865057e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74084)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 165093)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 85:E554[23])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The rebels looking-glasse: or, The traytors doome. Wherein is discovered the judgements of God upon the rebels and traytors in all ages: collected out of several histories both sacred &amp; profane. With a narration of this present rebellion, and of the horrid and execrable acts committed therin, and the judgements of God already observed to be saln upon the first actors and tormentors thereof. Published for the reducing of those that are already rebells, and deterring others from that sinne, / By a faithfull and loyall subject to the present king, and a lover of his country.</title>
                  <author>Faithfull and loyall subject to the present King.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 9th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:165093:1"/>
            <p>THE REBELS LOOKING-GLASSE: OR, THE TRAYTORS DOOME. VVherein is discovered the Iudgements of God upon Rebels and Traytors in all Ages: Collected out of several Histories both Sacred &amp; Profane. <hi>WITH</hi> A Narration of this present Rebellion, and of the horrid and execrable acts committed therein, and the judgments of God already observed to be faln upon the first actors and fomenters thereof. <hi>Published for the reducing of those that are alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Rebells, and deterring others from that sinne.</hi> By a faithfull and Loyall Subject to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent KING, and a Lover of His Country.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1649.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:165093:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:165093:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the</hi> Members <hi>of that</hi> Iunto <hi>that sit in the Commons House at</hi> VVestminster.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or so many of you were, till you <hi>tainted your Bloud with Rebellion;</hi> when you were called to sit in that <hi>House,</hi> you took not the <hi>Covenant,</hi> or <hi>Negative Oath,</hi> but the <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Allegeance</hi> and <hi>Supremacy,</hi> flat contrary to those other two; If the <hi>King</hi> were not <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame,</hi> you are <hi>forsworne;</hi> If He were, (as undoubtedly He was) you had no power to bring Him to <hi>Tryall,</hi> and wanting <hi>Power,</hi> (as by the Letter of the <hi>Law</hi> of this <hi>Land</hi> assuredly you did) His Execution was not <hi>Justice,</hi> but <hi>Murder.</hi> Though thoughts are free, yet to think evill of the <hi>King</hi> is condemned by <hi>Solomon,</hi> to speak evill of the <hi>King</hi> is <hi>Treason</hi> by the <hi>Law,</hi> to take up <hi>Armes</hi> against the <hi>King,</hi> it is against the expresse both of <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture</hi> and <hi>Law:</hi> surely then to <hi>Murder</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> must needs be <hi>Treason</hi> in the abstract: we have a long time justly termed you <hi>Rebells,</hi> but now we must call you <hi>Rebells</hi> in a more exalted note, and stile you <hi>Regicides.</hi> When you were summoned to that House, you were called to repaire, and not inlarge the breaches of the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> to strengthen; and not subvert <hi>Religion;</hi> to conserve, and not overthrow the <hi>Lawes;</hi> to consult with, and not confound His <hi>Majesty:</hi> in acting whereof, you have most impiously broken your <hi>Oath</hi> with <hi>God,</hi> your <hi>Allegeance</hi> to the <hi>King;</hi> your obedience to the
<pb facs="tcp:165093:3"/>
               <hi>Church,</hi> and the trust reposed in you by the <hi>People.</hi> It hath been the happinesse of former <hi>Parliaments,</hi> and their utmost industry, to preserve the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> with the <hi>Lawes</hi> and <hi>People</hi> thereof: It hath been your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall imployment, indefatigable paines, and esteemed happinesse to destroy the <hi>Kingdome, Lawes, People,</hi> and the preservers thereof. There are many amongst you learned in the <hi>Lawes,</hi> and if they have neglected their <hi>Duty,</hi> yet their tenacity cannot warrant your procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings; For that grave and <hi>learned Oracle</hi> of the <hi>Law, Judge Jenkins</hi> hath sufficiently explained the difficulties of the <hi>Law,</hi> and your <hi>Duties,</hi> whose paines you have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rewarded with a <hi>most long and loathsome imprisonment. For which, and other your most execrable and unparallelled impieties, you must expect to have the thunderbolts of Gods anger throwne down upon you;</hi> for <hi>God</hi> is a just <hi>God,</hi> and cannot <hi>lie,</hi> neither will he suffer those to goe unpunished, that not onely resist his <hi>Ordinance,</hi> but advance their own above his. The <hi>Presbyterians</hi> were the first that fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented this <hi>Rebellion</hi> against the <hi>King,</hi> and you see the heavy <hi>Judgement of God upon them:</hi> in so speedy snatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the power from them, when they thought themselves so securely the <hi>Lords</hi> of all: and <hi>Waller, Massey,</hi> and the rest, that were the great <hi>pillars</hi> of that cause, are now, you see, become the scorn and contempt both of friends and foes, and undoubtedly as you have been more vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and <hi>bloudy</hi> in your <hi>Rebellion</hi> then they, so your <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> shall be more <hi>fearfull:</hi> For prevention whereof, I have directed this little <hi>theater</hi> of <hi>Gods Judgements upon Rebells</hi> and <hi>Traytors in all Ages to you:</hi> that, when you see such small <hi>Rebellions</hi> and <hi>petty treasons</hi> so fearfully punished, you being conscious of the <hi>monstrousnesse</hi> of your <hi>execrable</hi> and <hi>unparallelled Treasons</hi> may endeavour
<pb facs="tcp:165093:3"/>to avoid your approaching Judgement, by a speedy desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting from your <hi>damnable designes.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sero medicina paratur</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cam mala per longas invaluere moras.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>I shall conclude with this advice, that you purge your <hi>House</hi> of all those <hi>Factious Members, that of late have illegally crept in, men, whose</hi> Principles are as base as their Births, and have no way to shake off the <hi>poverty of their parentage,</hi> but by <hi>Rapine,</hi> and <hi>Oppression</hi> of the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi> That you call home the young <hi>King;</hi> and seat Him in His Throne in <hi>Freedome, Safety,</hi> and <hi>Honour,</hi> that you deliver up <hi>Bradshaw, Cook,</hi> and others that had hands in the late Kings, your Soveraignes Murder, <hi>to speedy and impartiall Justice.</hi> That you endeavour your utmost to Disband the <hi>Army;</hi> who are a crew of <hi>beggarly Sectaries,</hi> the <hi>scum</hi> and <hi>offall</hi> of the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> and onely <hi>Disturbers of our quiet.</hi> That you sue to His <hi>Majesty for your Pardon, and crave an Act of Indemnity; and in so doing, you may save the effusion of much Christian Bloud, and render your selves, and your Country happy,</hi> which otherwise will spue them out as <hi>noisome rubbish,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver your <hi>remembrance</hi> to <hi>Posterity</hi> in an <hi>infamous</hi> and <hi>loathsome Character.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Vale.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:165093:4"/>
            <head>To <hi>Tho: Lord Fairfax, Baron</hi> of <hi>Came<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, Generall</hi> of the ARMY.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>ITs very probable, that the sight of this</hi> Epistle <hi>will pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sesse you with a double</hi> wonder, <hi>first that your servants, or rather</hi> slaves, <hi>the Commons, should be preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you, and then, that such a subject as this should be</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated <hi>to you; to the first I</hi> answer, <hi>that I have but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed my selfe to your practise, for if the</hi> Subject <hi>may be preferred above the</hi> KING, <hi>well may the</hi> servant <hi>before the</hi> Master. <hi>And to the second I</hi> answer, <hi>that I know no man fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to patronize this</hi> work <hi>then</hi> your selfe, <hi>who is the</hi> Ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leader <hi>of the greatest, most</hi> horrid, <hi>and</hi> Bloudy Rebellion, <hi>that ever was managed in any</hi> Age <hi>of the</hi> world, <hi>and have committed and countenanced such</hi> execrable <hi>and</hi> damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Acts, <hi>as the most</hi> Barbarous Rebell <hi>that ever drew a Sword in the most</hi> barbarous and Heathenish Age, <hi>would have blushed and trembled at the Relation thereof.</hi> My Lord, <hi>you must excuse me, if like a skilfull</hi> Chirurgion, I throughly lanch the festred wounds of your guilty Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science which is laden with ingratitude, breach of Faith, Perjury, Murder, Rebellion, and Regicide. <hi>Me thinkes, that if the principles of</hi> Loyalty <hi>and</hi> Conscience <hi>could not, yet those of gratitude, (ingratitude being a sinne so much</hi> abhorred <hi>by the very</hi> Heathens, <hi>that they esteemed it</hi> worthy <hi>of</hi> death) <hi>might have prevailed with you, to have been</hi> so far frō drawing your sword in Rebellion, that you would have turned it into the brests of Rebels. <hi>That Title
<pb facs="tcp:165093:4"/>of</hi> Honour <hi>which you now</hi> enjoy (<hi>For your</hi> Additions, <hi>are rather the stiles of shame and infamy, then of</hi> Honour <hi>and</hi> Renowne, <hi>was, by His</hi> Majesty, <hi>conferred upon your</hi> Noble Grand-father; <hi>who undoubtedly so abhorred</hi> Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, <hi>that had he known what</hi> Vipers <hi>he had to his</hi> Sonne <hi>and</hi> Grand-sonne, <hi>he would not onely have made you the heires of his</hi> curses, <hi>but have</hi> loathed <hi>his very</hi> Loyns <hi>for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting such a</hi> pestilent Issue; <hi>the same</hi> King <hi>that conferred on your</hi> Family <hi>the</hi> Honour <hi>of</hi> Lordship, <hi>begirt you like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise with the</hi> Sword <hi>of</hi> Knighthood: <hi>which high favour you have ingratefully rewarded with the losse of the</hi> Donors life: <hi>It were but vaine for me to refresh your memory by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peating your Oath of</hi> Allegeance <hi>and</hi> Supremacy, <hi>and your</hi> Protestation, <hi>which you have most palpably</hi> broken <hi>by</hi> taking up Armes against your Soveraigne, <hi>and</hi> killing <hi>and</hi> slaying His most faithfull and Loyall Subjects, <hi>but even your</hi> Solemne League and Convenant, <hi>and that</hi> so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne ingagement which you and your Commanders gave His Majesty upon your Honours <hi>at</hi> Newmarket, <hi>and ratified with</hi> Vowes <hi>and</hi> Oathes, <hi>that you would settle His</hi> Majesty <hi>in His</hi> Throne <hi>with</hi> security, <hi>and</hi> Honour <hi>to</hi> Himselfe and His Posterity; <hi>which your have most basely and</hi> dishonourably broken; <hi>For it was you,</hi> My Lord, <hi>that signed that</hi> Remonstrance, <hi>and sent it with your</hi> mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natory letter to the Houses, wherein you desired, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther commanded, that His Majesty, whom your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannerly language stiled the Grand &amp; Capitall Enemy of this Nation, might be brought to slaughter, which you mis-called Justice. <hi>In conclusion, although as</hi> Pilate <hi>once did, so you would now wash your</hi> hands from the guilt of your Soveraigns innocent bloud, <hi>yet you and your</hi> Sectarian Army <hi>are certainly guilty of that</hi> barbarous Murder, <hi>which was a</hi> cruell Execution, <hi>an</hi> inhumane
<pb facs="tcp:165093:5"/>cruelty, a brutish immanity, a devilish brutishnesse, <hi>and an</hi> hyperbolicall, <hi>yea, an</hi> hyperdiabolicall devilishnesse, <hi>so that what cursed</hi> Shimei <hi>did once as a reproach falsly cast upon</hi> David, <hi>the blessed</hi> people <hi>of</hi> God <hi>may justly throw upon you, and say, Thou man of</hi> Bloud: <hi>And now</hi> My Lord, <hi>having</hi> searched your wounds, <hi>and, I hope, let forth the corruption; I will prescribe you a method of cure, which must be by applying the plaister of</hi> Repentance <hi>to them; and washing your</hi> bloud-stained Conscience <hi>with the</hi> teares <hi>of</hi> Contrition, <hi>For which end onely, I protest that I, who cannot</hi> honour <hi>your</hi> Family <hi>for your sake, yet cannot but</hi> honour <hi>you for your</hi> Families sake, <hi>have Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this</hi> little book <hi>to your</hi> Lordship; <hi>hoping that when you read the successe of</hi> former Rebellions, <hi>your</hi> Lorship <hi>will repent of yours, and performe the</hi> Oath <hi>to the</hi> Sonne <hi>which your sware to His</hi> Father: <hi>in doing whereof, you will remove that cloud of</hi> Bloud <hi>which</hi> darkens <hi>the ancient</hi> splendour <hi>of your</hi> Noble Family, <hi>and pay the debt which you owe to the</hi> Kingdome <hi>for their</hi> ruine <hi>in making them to become your</hi> debters <hi>for the</hi> restauration <hi>to right; and your</hi> Lorship <hi>and we be at once happy, in living quietly, and</hi> Religiously <hi>under the peaceable Government of our</hi> Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous King <hi>CHARLES</hi> the Second, <hi>whom</hi> God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>VALE.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:165093:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Rebells Looking-glasse:</hi> OR, <hi>The Traytors Doome.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>INGS <hi>are Gods Vice-gerents;</hi> who doe imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately present the <hi>Person,</hi> and exercise the power of <hi>God</hi> upon Earth: and every evill act committed against the KING, is a loud-spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>Blasphemy</hi> against the divine <hi>majesty</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> forasmuch as from thence, the <hi>majesty</hi> of <hi>Kings is derived.</hi> As it is required both by <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Reason,</hi> that Children should <hi>honour</hi> and reverence their <hi>Parents:</hi> so it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisite and necessary, that <hi>Subjects</hi> should performe their <hi>duty</hi> of <hi>Honour and Allegiance to their Kings.</hi> Where the <hi>word</hi> of a <hi>King is, there is Power,</hi> And who may say unto him what dost thou? saith the Spirit of <hi>God</hi> by the <hi>mouth of Solomon. Rebellion</hi> is as the <hi>sinne of witch-craft,</hi> that is, is as abominable in <hi>Gods</hi> sight as <hi>witch-craft.</hi> For <hi>demonstration</hi> of which truth, I shall present you with a view of <hi>Gods Justice, manifested in the world upon Rebels</hi> and <hi>Traytors, both in elder and latter times;</hi> and shew both out of <hi>sacred</hi> and <hi>profane Histories,</hi> how the <hi>tempest</hi> of <hi>Gods wrath</hi> hath been degrandinated upon the heads of the <hi>mighty ones of this world,</hi> that <hi>have been disobedient, and Rebellious against their Princes:</hi> And how his vengeance hath pursued those <hi>Malefactors to their shame and confusion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The dismall and unparalleld <hi>Judgement of God upon Corah, Dathan and Abiram, and the Rebels under their Command,</hi> who set themselves against <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Aaron;</hi> is not unknown to any who have been conversant in the Book of <hi>God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numbers 26.</note> Likewise the <hi>Children of Israel,</hi> who <hi>slandred</hi> and <hi>mutined against Moses,</hi> their
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:165093:6"/>
               <hi>Soveraigne Magistate</hi> and <hi>Conductor,</hi> that so meekly had brought them out of the <hi>Land of Aegypt,</hi> by the speciall <hi>command of God;</hi> and charged him with conspiring the murder of those <hi>Rebels,</hi> whom not he, but <hi>God</hi> for their <hi>pride and stubbornnesse,</hi> had <hi>rooted</hi> out and <hi>destroyed. Felt the fury of Gods displeasure for this their fact, who scourged them with a most grievous plague, whereof dyed about fourteen thousand, and seaven hundred persons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Strange was the malice of <hi>Absolom</hi> in <hi>rebelling</hi> so furiously against his <hi>Father and Soveraign Lord King David,</hi> and as strange was his <hi>punishment:</hi> for having in Battle lost the day, and being in flight from the pursute of his <hi>Enemies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 18.</note> was overtaken by <hi>Gods Judgement,</hi> from which he could not <hi>flie;</hi> for riding along the forrest to save himself, his <hi>Mule</hi> carrying him under a <hi>thick Oake,</hi> left him hanging by the <hi>Haire upon a bough, betwixt Heaven and Earth,</hi> untill being found by <hi>Joab,</hi> he was wounded to death. An accident strange and wonderfull, yet such an one, as <hi>God</hi> himselfe provided to punish this <hi>Rebellious wretch;</hi> which fearfull spectacle of <hi>Gods Judgement</hi> may serve to terrifie the most impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent <hi>Rebell</hi> from this <hi>horrible sinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Achitophell,</hi> who forsook his <hi>Soveraigne Leige Lord, and anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted King,</hi> and with his counsell and presence aided <hi>Absolom</hi> in his <hi>Rebellion; God</hi> in anger, suffered him to be his own executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner, for he fell into <hi>dispaire, and hanged himselfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Shimei,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 16.</note> who in the time of <hi>Absoloms Rebellion,</hi> in his wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and perverse humour, instead of <hi>Service due unto his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne in that extremity;</hi> presented himselfe not as a <hi>Subject,</hi> but as a <hi>Railer,</hi> cursing him with most reproachfull <hi>tearmes,</hi> and throwing stones at him, and his followers in most <hi>Trayterous manner:</hi> for which <hi>Rebellious act,</hi> though <hi>David</hi> did not question him, yet <hi>God</hi> would not exempt him from punishment; for in the end, his wickednesse fell upon his own <hi>head,</hi> and destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on overtook him by desert of another fault, at the command of <hi>King Solomon.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The punishment of <hi>Shiba,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 20.</note> the <hi>sonne of Bichri</hi> tarryed not so long, who with a proud and audacious <hi>heart</hi> stirred up the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test part of <hi>Israel</hi> to <hi>Rebell against David,</hi> when he thought to have been most at quiet; for he enjoyed not long his <hi>disloyall enterprise,</hi> for being speedily pursued by <hi>Davids servants,</hi> and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:165093:6"/>besieged in the <hi>City Abell, his head was cut off by the Citizens, and throwne over the wall,</hi> as a just reward for his <hi>Rebellious Act.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to let passe these <hi>sacred Histories,</hi> and come to <hi>prophane,</hi> yet probable and more neer examples. <hi>Theodorick,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Albert Crautz.</note>
               <hi>King</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Irminfride, King</hi> of <hi>Thuringia,</hi> being profest <hi>Foes,</hi> after many cruell <hi>Battels</hi> fought, <hi>Irminfride</hi> was conquered by <hi>King Theodorick,</hi> who being subdued, sued for <hi>pardon</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lease</hi> at the <hi>Conquerours hand,</hi> who was so farre from pittying his estate, that he corrupted one <hi>Iringus a noble man,</hi> and <hi>Irmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frides Subject</hi> to <hi>murder his Soveraigne, which he performed knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling before Theodorick, running him through with his sword at his back:</hi> which traiterous deed being finished, <hi>King Theodorick</hi> though the promoter of it, yet so <hi>abhorred</hi> the <hi>Actor,</hi> that he commanded him forthwith to avoid his presence, for he could not put any trust in him, that had betrayed his owne <hi>Master.</hi> At which words <hi>Iringus</hi> (mad with anger and rage) ran at <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorick also, with purpose to have slaine him;</hi> but his <hi>hand missing the mark, returned his sword into his owne Bowels,</hi> so that he fell down dead upon his <hi>Masters Carcasse. A notable and wonderfull Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and an example worthy to be written in golden letters, and to be read and remembred of every one, to teach menallegeance and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to their Princes,</hi> lest more sudden destruction then this fall upon them.</p>
            <p>After the death of <hi>Jeronimus, King of Siracusa, Andronodorus</hi> and <hi>Themistius</hi> provoked by their <hi>Wives</hi> descending of the <hi>Bloud Royall,</hi> affected an usurpation of the <hi>Crowne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Titus Livius.</note> and wrought much hurt to the <hi>Common-wealth;</hi> but their practises being dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, the Pretors (by the consent of the Senators) <hi>slew them both in the Market-place, as rotten members of their common body, and therefore fit to be cut off.</hi> And when they understood how their <hi>Wives, Damarata</hi> and <hi>Harmonia</hi> were the incensers of this mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, they sent to <hi>kill them also:</hi> yea, and <hi>Heraclia, Harmoniaes sister,</hi> guiltlesse of the <hi>crime,</hi> (for no other cause but because she was her Sister) was <hi>pluckt</hi> from the <hi>Altar,</hi> and slaine in the <hi>tumult</hi> with two of her <hi>Daughters that were Virgins.</hi> Thus is <hi>Treason plauged,</hi> not onely in <hi>Traytors</hi> themselves, but also in those that are <hi>linked</hi> unto them in <hi>friendship,</hi> and <hi>affinity.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:165093:7"/>
            <p>What notable <hi>Treasons</hi> did <hi>Hadrian</hi> the fourth, <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> practice against the <hi>Emperour, Frederick Barbarossa,</hi> yet all was frustrate, For the <hi>Lord protected the Emperour,</hi> and punished the <hi>Traytour with a sudden and strange death;</hi> for he was choaked with a <hi>Flie</hi> which went down his <hi>throat,</hi> and <hi>stopped his breath,</hi> and could by no meanes be pull'd out till it made an end of him. Besides, many others that went about the same practice, were brought to notable <hi>Destructions:</hi> as that counterfeit <hi>fool</hi> whom the <hi>Italians</hi> set on to <hi>murder Frederick in his chamber,</hi> which had been performed, had he not <hi>leaped</hi> out of a <hi>window</hi> into a <hi>River,</hi> and so <hi>saved his life:</hi> for the <hi>foole</hi> being taken, was throwne headlong out of the same <hi>window,</hi> and so <hi>broke his neck.</hi> As also an <hi>Arabian Doctor, a grand poysoner,</hi> who going about to infect with <hi>poyson</hi> his <hi>Bridle, Saddle, Spurs,</hi> and <hi>Stirrops,</hi> that as soone as he should but touch them he might be <hi>poysoned,</hi> was dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered and hanged for his labour.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Emanuel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Otto Frisingensis de rebus Freder. Prin.</hi> lib. 1. c. 47</note>
               <hi>Emperour of Constantinople, lay about Antioch with an Army prepared against the Turk,</hi> one of his chiefest <hi>Officers,</hi> namely his <hi>Chancellour,</hi> put in practise this notable piece of <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi> against him: he waged three <hi>desperate young men with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite summe of money to kill him</hi> upon an appointed day, and then with a band of <hi>Souldiers determined to possesse himself of the Crown, and the City, and to slay all that any way crossed his purpose.</hi> But the <hi>Treason</hi> being discovered secretly to the <hi>Empresse,</hi> she acquainted her <hi>Lord</hi> with it, who took the <hi>three Traytors,</hi> and put them all to <hi>cruell deaths: and as for the Chancellour, he first bored out his eyes, and plucking his tongue through his throat, tormented him to death with a most rigorous and miserable punishment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Scribonianus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lanquet Chron.</note> a <hi>Captaine of the Romans in Dalmatia, rebelled against the Emperour Claudius, and named himselfe Emperour in the Army;</hi> but his <hi>Rebellion</hi> was <hi>miraculously punished,</hi> for though the whole <hi>Army</hi> favoured him very much, yet they could not by any meanes spread their Banners, or remove their Standards out of their <hi>places,</hi> as long as he was called by the name of <hi>Emperour,</hi> with which miracle being moved they turned their <hi>Loves</hi> into <hi>hatred,</hi> and their <hi>liking</hi> into <hi>loathing,</hi> so that whom lately they saluted as <hi>Emperour,</hi> him now they <hi>murdered as a Traytor.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:165093:7"/>
            <p>To rehearse all the Traytors that have conspired against their <hi>Kings</hi> from the <hi>Conquest</hi> to this <hi>present Age,</hi> were unnecessary, and almost impossible: yet that their destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on may be our <hi>instruction;</hi> and the curse of God upon <hi>Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> be made more manifest, I will cite some of the chiefest of them.</p>
            <p>In the year 1264 <hi>Simon Montford Earl of Leicester,</hi> with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse other <hi>Earls</hi> and <hi>Barons,</hi> upon diverse faire and specious pretences, for <hi>Religion, and the common good,</hi> raised a <hi>Rebellion</hi> against their <hi>Soveraigne Lord King Henry the Third;</hi> and in a Battle near <hi>Lewes</hi> in <hi>Sussex,</hi> became masters of the Field, took prisoners the <hi>King, Prince,</hi> the <hi>Earl of Cornwall,</hi> Brother to the <hi>King,</hi> and his Sonne, together with the <hi>Earls</hi> of <hi>Arundell,</hi> and <hi>Hereford,</hi> and <hi>diverse Scottish Lords,</hi> had them in possession a year and a half, at length, by the providence of <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>Prince</hi> made an escape from the <hi>Castle</hi> of <hi>Hereford,</hi> where he was <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soner, gathered an Army,</hi> and at <hi>Evesham,</hi> neer <hi>Worcester, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threw the Rebels Army, redeemed the King his Father, slew the Earl of Liecester their Ring-leader, and an eleven other Lords, the ensuing Parliament dis-inherited all their adherents, and the Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doners, who in all Ages were either the parents, or nurses of Rebellion, lost their Liberties,</hi> the Family of the <hi>Montfords</hi> were expell'd the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> and driven to seek their fortunes elsewhere; so just is <hi>God</hi> in revenging himselfe on those, that <hi>Rebell against his Vice-gerents.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the year 1275. <hi>Lewlin, Prince of Wales Rebelled against King Edward the First,</hi> and after much adoe was taken by <hi>Sir Roger Mortimer,</hi> and his Head set upon the <hi>Tower of London.</hi> After the same manner was his Brother <hi>David</hi> served, <hi>Ries</hi> and <hi>Madock</hi> had the same reward for stirring up the <hi>Welshmen</hi> to a <hi>Rebellion,</hi> No better measure had the <hi>Scots,</hi> who having of their own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord committed the Government of their Kingdome to <hi>King Edward,</hi> after the death of <hi>Alexander,</hi> (who broke his neck with a fall from his Horse, and left no issue male) and sworn fealty unto him: yet dispenced with their <hi>Oath,</hi> by the <hi>Popes Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission,</hi> and the <hi>Frenchmens incitement,</hi> and <hi>rebelled</hi> diverse times against <hi>King Edward:</hi> for he overcame them sundry times, and <hi>slew at one time</hi> 32000. <hi>and took diverse of their nobility prisoners.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:165093:8"/>
            <p>In the Raigne of <hi>King Henry the Fourth</hi> there <hi>Rebelled</hi> at one time against him, <hi>John Holland, Duke of Excester,</hi> with the <hi>Dukes</hi> of <hi>Aumerl, Surrey, Salisbury,</hi> and <hi>Glocester;</hi> and at another time <hi>Thomas Percy Earl of Worcester,</hi> and <hi>Henry Lord Percy,</hi> sonne to the <hi>Earl of Northumberland,</hi> at another time <hi>Richard Scroop, Arch-bishop of Yorke,</hi> and diverse others of the house of the <hi>Lord Newbray;</hi> at another time <hi>Henry Earl of Northumberland, and the Lord Bardolph:</hi> and lastly, <hi>Rice ap Dee,</hi> and <hi>Owen Glen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour</hi> two <hi>Welchmen:</hi> all which were either slaine as <hi>Henry Lord Percy,</hi> or <hi>beheaded as the rest of these</hi> (though by Birth Noble, yet by practice Ignoble) <hi>Rebels;</hi> or starved to death as <hi>Owen Glendour</hi> was in the <hi>Mountaines of Wales,</hi> after he had devoured his own <hi>Flesh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Raigne of <hi>Henry the Fifth, Richard Earl of Cambridge, Sir Richard Scroop, Lord high Treasurer of England, and Sir Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Gray were beheaded for Treason.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To passe over the time of the residue of the <hi>Kings,</hi> wherein many examples of <hi>Treasons,</hi> and punishments upon them are extant, and come nearer unto our owne Age, let us consider the wonderfull providence of <hi>God,</hi> in discovering the notorious <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons,</hi> which were so often contrived against <hi>Q. Eliz:</hi> of <hi>happy me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory,</hi> and <hi>protecting</hi> her so violently from the violence of them all. First, to begin with the <hi>Earles</hi> of <hi>Northumberland and Westmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who in the <hi>eleven year of her Raigne, began a Rebellion in the North,</hi> pretending sometimes their purpose to be to defend the <hi>Queenes Person</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> from the invasion of Strangers, and sometimes for Conscience sake to seek <hi>Reformation</hi> and <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion;</hi> under colour whereof, they got together <hi>an Army of men, to the number of six thousand Souldiers:</hi> against whom marched the <hi>Earl of Sussex Lieutenant of the North,</hi> and the <hi>Earl of War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick</hi> sent by the <hi>Queen</hi> to his aide: whose approach struck such a terrour into their hearts, that the two <hi>Earles,</hi> with diverse of the <hi>Arch-rebels,</hi> fled into <hi>Scotland,</hi> leaving the rest of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany a prey unto their <hi>Enemies,</hi> whereof <hi>threescore and six,</hi> or thereabout, were hanged at <hi>Durham.</hi> As for the <hi>Earles, Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumberland</hi> was after taken in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and beheaded at <hi>Yorke. Westmerland</hi> fled into another <hi>Country,</hi> and left his House and Family destroyed, and undone by his <hi>Folly.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:165093:8"/>
            <p>Not long after <hi>John Throgmorton, Thomas Brooke, George Red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> and diverse other Gentlemen at <hi>Norwich</hi> pretended a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion</hi> under colour of suppressing <hi>Strangers,</hi> being discovered by one of their own conspiracy, <hi>Tho. Ket,</hi> were executed at <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich</hi> for <hi>their paines:</hi> To the same end came <hi>Francis Throgmorton,</hi> whose <hi>Treacheries,</hi> as they were abominable, and touching the <hi>Queenes</hi> own <hi>Person,</hi> so were they disclosed not without the speciall providence of <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But above all, that vile and ungratefull <hi>Traytor William Parry,</hi> upon whom the <hi>Queen</hi> had plentifully powred her <hi>liberality,</hi> deserveth to have his <hi>shame written in an indeleable Character:</hi> whose horrible <hi>Treason</hi> being discovered, he justly pay'd the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute of his <hi>life</hi> in recompence thereof. The justice of <hi>God</hi> did likewise appear in the end of a <hi>second Earl</hi> of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> who being attainted for <hi>Treason,</hi> became his owne <hi>executioner, and slew himselfe in prison.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Notorious were the <hi>conspiracies</hi> of those <hi>Arch traytors, Ballard, Babington, Savadge,</hi> and <hi>Tilney,</hi> yet <hi>God</hi> brought them downe, and made them spectacles to the <hi>world</hi> of his <hi>justice.</hi> Likewise Dr. <hi>Lopus</hi> (the <hi>Queenes Physitian</hi>) that <hi>treacherous villaine,</hi> who a long time had not onely been an <hi>Intelligencer</hi> to the <hi>Pope,</hi> and <hi>King of Spaine,</hi> of our <hi>English Counsailes,</hi> but also had poysoned many <hi>Noble Men,</hi> and went about also to <hi>poyson the Queen her selfe,</hi> being surprised in his <hi>Treachery, was brought to sudden de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As it is not lawfull for Children to <hi>rebell</hi> against their Parents, though they be <hi>cruell</hi> and <hi>unnaturall,</hi> so also it is unlawfull for <hi>subjects</hi> to withstand their <hi>Princes,</hi> though they be burdensome unto them: for no <hi>subject</hi> ought to shake off the <hi>yoke of subjection and obedience due unto his Prince,</hi> or exempt himselfe from any <hi>Tax</hi> by that Authority imposed. And generally in all <hi>actions</hi> we ought with all <hi>patience</hi> to endure what burden is laid upon us, without so much as discontent: for those that have other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise behaved themselves, these following examples will set forth their <hi>reward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the year of our Lord 1304.
<note place="margin">Nich. Gil.</note> after that <hi>Guy Earl of Flanders having rebelled against Philip the Faire, his Soveraigne, was by strength of Armes reduced into subjection, and constrained to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:165093:9"/>himselfe, and his two sonnes prisoners into his hands:</hi> the <hi>Fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mings</hi> made an insurrection against the <hi>King,</hi> because of a <hi>Tax</hi> which he had set upon their <hi>Ships</hi> that arrived at certain Havens: upon this occasion grew a <hi>Warre,</hi> wherein were fought diverse <hi>Battels,</hi> and sundry overthrowes on either side, yet at last the <hi>King</hi> remained <hi>Conquerour;</hi> and the <hi>Flemings</hi> (for a reward of their Rebellion) lost in the <hi>Battle six and thirty thousand men,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides <hi>Prisoners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Two years after this <hi>Flemish</hi> stir,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nich. Gil.</hi> vol. 1</note>
               <hi>there arose a hurlyburly of the rascall and basest sort of people at Paris,</hi> because of the alteration of their <hi>Coyns,</hi> who not satisfied with the pillage of their <hi>houses,</hi> whom they supposed to be causers of the said alteration, came in great numbers before the <hi>Kings Pallace at his lodging in the Temple,</hi> with such an hideous noise and outrage, that all the day after, neither the <hi>King,</hi> nor <hi>any of his Officers durst stirre forth;</hi> and they grew further to that overflow of <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>insolency,</hi> that the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vision which was prepared for the <hi>Kings Table,</hi> was by them shamefully throwne under feet, and trampled upon in disdaine: But three or four dayes after this <hi>Tumult</hi> was <hi>appeased, many of them for their paines were hanged before their owne doores, and in the City Gates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the time of <hi>Charles the sixt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Froiss.</hi> vol. 2. cap. 97.</note>
               <hi>King of France,</hi> the <hi>Flandrians</hi> and Inhabitants of <hi>Gaunt</hi> made an insurrection against <hi>Lewes, Earl of Flanders, their Lord,</hi> for diverse <hi>Taxes</hi> and <hi>Tributes</hi> which he had lay'd upon them. The matter came to be decided by <hi>blowes, much bloud was shed,</hi> and many losses endured on both sides; as a meanes appointed by <hi>God</hi> to chastise as well the one as the other. The <hi>Gaunts</hi> overthrew the <hi>Earls Army,</hi> and in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suite of their <hi>Victory</hi> took <hi>Burges,</hi> whither the <hi>Earl was gone for safety; and lying in a poor womans house was constrained</hi> (in the habit of a beggar) <hi>to flie the City.</hi> Till at length <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>sixt</hi> sent <hi>an Army to his succour,</hi> by whose support he overcame those <hi>Rebels</hi> in a <hi>Battle</hi> at <hi>Rose Bee,</hi> to the number of <hi>fourty thousand:</hi> and the body of <hi>Philip Artevill,</hi> their <hi>Grand Ryoter slaine in the throng,</hi> he caused to be <hi>hanged on a tree;</hi> And this was the end of the cruell <hi>Tragedy,</hi> the Country being brought againe to the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of their <hi>Old Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1525. certaine <hi>Husbandman of Sovabey</hi> began to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:165093:9"/>stand in resistance against the <hi>Earl of Lupsfen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sleid.</hi> lib. 4.</note> by reason of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine burdens, wherewith they complained themselves to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laid; their neighbours seeing this, enterprised the like against their <hi>Lords:</hi> And so upon this small beginning, there grew a most dangerous <hi>commotion,</hi> that spread it selfe over all <hi>Almaine;</hi> the Sedition thus increasing in all quarters, and the <hi>Swaines</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>fourty thousand strong,</hi> making their owne <hi>Liberty,</hi> and the <hi>Gospels</hi> a cloake to cover their <hi>Treason</hi> and <hi>Rebellion,</hi> did not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fight with the <hi>Romane Catholicks,</hi> but with all other without respect, as well in <hi>Sovabe</hi> as in <hi>Franconia,</hi> they destroyed the greater part of the <hi>Nobility, sacked, and burnt many Castles and Fortresses, to the number of two hundred, and put to death the Earl of Helfestin, whom they made to passe through the pikes.</hi> But at length their strength was broken, and themselves discomfitted and torne in pieces, with a most horrible <hi>massacre of more then eighteen thousand. During this Sedition there were slaine on each side, fifty thousand men. Geismer</hi> the <hi>Captaine</hi> of the <hi>Sovabian Swaines,</hi> having betaken himselfe to <hi>flight,</hi> got over the <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines to Padua,</hi> where for <hi>Treason</hi> he was made away.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1381. in the <hi>Raigne of King Richard the Second,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Stow. Chron.</note> the <hi>Commons</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> (and especially of <hi>Kent</hi> and <hi>Essex</hi>) by reason of a <hi>Tax</hi> that was set upon them, assembled in <hi>Rebellion</hi> on <hi>Black-heath,</hi> to the number of <hi>threescore thousand and upwards:</hi> which <hi>Rebellious rout</hi> had none but base <hi>mechanick Fellowes</hi> for their <hi>Captaines,</hi> as <hi>Wat Tylour, Jack Straw,</hi> and <hi>Tom Miller,</hi> but yet they were the cause of much trouble and disquietnesse in the Realme, and chiefly about the <hi>City of London,</hi> where they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted many <hi>outrages</hi> in destroying the <hi>Savoy,</hi> and other places, and behaved themselves in <hi>Smithfield most proudly,</hi> and <hi>irreverent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly towards the King:</hi> but by the <hi>Heroick spirit of Will. Walworth, then Lord Mayor of London,</hi> (who arrested their chief Captaine in the midst of them) that rude company was dicomfitted, and the Ring-leaders of them received condigne punishment.</p>
            <p>In the Raigne of <hi>Henry the Seventh, King of England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Stow. Chron.</note> A great commotion was stirred up in <hi>England,</hi> by the <hi>Commons</hi> of the <hi>North,</hi> by reason of a <hi>Tax</hi> which was levyed of the <hi>tenth penny</hi> of all mens <hi>Lands</hi> and <hi>Goods</hi> within the <hi>Land,</hi> in the which the <hi>Earl of Northumberland was slaine:</hi> But their <hi>rash attempt</hi> was
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:165093:10"/>soone broken, and <hi>Chamberlaine</hi> their <hi>Captaine,</hi> with diverse others slaine at <hi>Yorke</hi> for the same.</p>
            <p>In the same <hi>Kings Raigne</hi> the <hi>Cornishmen Rebelled,</hi> under the conduct of the <hi>Lord Audley,</hi> and by wofull experience felt the same <hi>Scourge;</hi> for the <hi>King</hi> met them upon <hi>Black-heath,</hi> and discomfitting their <hi>Troupes,</hi> took their <hi>Captains</hi> and <hi>Ring-leaders,</hi> and put them to most <hi>deserved Deaths.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is worthy of observation, that throughout the holy Histories of sacred Scripture ever after any Treason, the holy Ghost presently sets downe the punishments of Traytors, as it were purposely to signifie how God hates those Rebells that resist his owne Ordinance: and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though God may for a time deferre his punishments, yet at last they shall assuredly fall heavy upon them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edward the Second, King of England,</hi> by the procurement of <hi>Isabell</hi> his <hi>Wife,</hi> and <hi>Roger Mortimer, Earl of March,</hi> being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justly deposed from his <hi>Crowne</hi> and <hi>Dignities, Edward his Eldest sonne as next Heire,</hi> tooke upon him the <hi>Regall State: Mortimer</hi> was afterwards beheaded for <hi>Treason,</hi> and <hi>King Edward</hi> himself, though he were but <hi>fourteen yeares</hi> of <hi>Age</hi> when his Father was <hi>deposed,</hi> and had no hand in that <hi>Trayterous Act,</hi> and was so farre from approving of it, that when he came to <hi>Age</hi> he puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed the <hi>Actors;</hi> yet <hi>God,</hi> to manifest his <hi>wrath</hi> against <hi>Treason,</hi> though he inflicted no <hi>personall punishment</hi> upon the <hi>King.</hi> yet not one of his <hi>Children,</hi> though be had a very numerous <hi>Issue,</hi> ever sate in the <hi>Throne of England;</hi> And his Grand-child that <hi>succee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him,</hi> was likewise unjustly deposed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, who contrary to all <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>Equity,</hi> by force of <hi>Armes deposed King Richard the Second,</hi> and took upon himself the <hi>Regall Title,</hi> was continnally <hi>plauged</hi> with a <hi>troubled Conscience,</hi> and <hi>violent Traytors,</hi> had a <hi>turbulent Raign,</hi> a <hi>riatous Sonne,</hi> and <hi>his Crowne taken from him before he dyed:</hi> For upon his Death-bed falling into a trance, he lay as though all his spirits had forsaken him, insomuch that all there present imagined him <hi>dead,</hi> and covered his <hi>face.</hi> The <hi>Prince,</hi> his <hi>Sonne,</hi> having notice thereof, came and took away the <hi>Crown,</hi> and <hi>departed.</hi> The <hi>King</hi> not long after reviving, <hi>asked</hi> for the <hi>Crown,</hi> and hearing the <hi>Prince had taken it, sends for him,</hi> and in an angry <hi>dialect de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands the reason of that his presumption:</hi> to whom the <hi>Prince</hi> with
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:165093:10"/>a confident <hi>brow</hi> made <hi>answer,</hi> That in his, and all mens <hi>Judgement</hi> there present he was <hi>dead,</hi> and then I being next Heire apparent to the same, took it as my <hi>indubitate Right,</hi> not as yours, but <hi>mine;</hi> well said the <hi>King,</hi> and fighed, Fair Sonne, what Right I had to it <hi>God knoweth.</hi> An undoubted token of <hi>Gods Judgement,</hi> that as he had <hi>Rebelliously snatched</hi> the <hi>Crown</hi> from his <hi>Soveraigne Leige Lord,</hi> and <hi>Trayterously caused him to be murdered; so his own Son should take it frō him while he was yet alive, to perplex his mind, and fill his guilty soul with horrours at the hour of his death, and send him with an unquiet Conscience to his Grave:</hi> Nor did the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment rest here, for revenge prosecuted his <hi>Childrens Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> and their Issue, even <hi>King Henry the Sixt,</hi> who though a most <hi>Gracious, Just, and Religious King,</hi> yet as his before-named <hi>Grand-father</hi> had snatched the <hi>Scepter</hi> from his <hi>Soveraignes hand,</hi> so was he most contemptibly pluckt from his Imperiall <hi>Throne</hi> in the <hi>Parliament House, deposed</hi> and <hi>Imprisoned:</hi> and though he was againe restored, yet he was afterward <hi>Deposed, Imprisoned,</hi> and <hi>Murdered, his Queen,</hi> as a <hi>vagabond,</hi> thrust forth of the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> and the <hi>Prince,</hi> his <hi>Sonne, stab'd</hi> in <hi>Twexbury,</hi> so just is <hi>God</hi> in <hi>revenging Treason,</hi> and <hi>Regicide</hi> upon the <hi>Actors,</hi> and their <hi>Posterity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What reward <hi>Richard the Third, King of England,</hi> had for his <hi>Rebellious usurpation of his true Soveraignes Crowne;</hi> those who have but any acquaintance with our <hi>English Histories</hi> cannot be <hi>ignorant.</hi> Who, contrary to the principles of <hi>Humanity, Loyalty,</hi> and <hi>Honesty, Murdered his Soveraign Lord King Edward the Fifth,</hi> and <hi>Richard, Duke of York, his Brother,</hi> and seated himselfe in the Throne <hi>Royall of England,</hi> but small <hi>Joy</hi> had he of his <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and little glory in his <hi>Kingly Majesty,</hi> the splendour of whose rayes was clouded by the strict and just edict of the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Kings,</hi> who fixed upon him the <hi>Markes of his heavy displeasure,</hi> for he was continually affrighted with the perplexities of a guilty Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: for during the time of his short and turbulent Raign, which continued not much above <hi>two years</hi> he scarce enjoyed one <hi>houres quiet,</hi> not daring to trust any, &amp; suspecting for false his most trusty Friends, even those that were his partners in <hi>Rebellion</hi> and <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der:</hi> and as his <hi>Life,</hi> so was his <hi>Death, rufull,</hi> for he was most <hi>cruelly slaine</hi> in the <hi>Battel of Bosworth field neer Leicester: his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:165093:11"/>Body without any Royall pomp being stark naked, all mangled and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>smeared with bloud and dust, without so much as the least rag to cover his privities, was trussed behind Bryan Senigleer his owne Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sevant at Armes, like a calfe, his head and armes hanging on one side of the horse, his legs on the other, and so was brought to Leicester, where for a spectacle of hate and scorne, by the space of two dayes he lay bare and un-interred:</hi> At last by the charity of the <hi>Gray Fryers</hi> there, without any <hi>Funerall Pomp,</hi> scarce with ordinary <hi>solemnity,</hi> he was <hi>inhumed</hi> in their <hi>monastery</hi> there.</p>
            <p>I might proceed with the <hi>Gowries conspiracy,</hi> and the <hi>Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder Treason,</hi> and the most <hi>apparent testimonies of Gods wrath upon the contrivers, but those as the rest beforementioned, being but weak and veniall crimes in respect of that which is to follow, I will let them passe, and conclude with the most horrid, monstrous, and bloudy Rebellion,</hi> the most unheard of <hi>Tragick, and damnable piece of Treason, Acted by the most perfidious, perjured,</hi> and <hi>execrable Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> that ever trod upon the face of the <hi>Earth.</hi> In the Year <hi>one thousand six hundred and fourty,</hi> A <hi>Year</hi> of most <hi>wofull</hi> and <hi>unhappy memory</hi> began the present <hi>Parliament,</hi> which is the greatest and most <hi>destroying Plague,</hi> with which <hi>God</hi> ever visited this <hi>Nation:</hi> For they not having <hi>God</hi> before their eyes, <hi>studyed</hi> their own <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement,</hi> not the <hi>Glory</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Honour of their Soveraigne,</hi> and pursued (not the preservation, but) ruine of <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Church.</hi> And that they might manifest their <hi>arrogarcy</hi> to the <hi>whole world,</hi> they presumed to demand that of their <hi>Soveraigne,</hi> which was neither fit for <hi>Subjects</hi> to <hi>aske,</hi> nor a <hi>King</hi> to <hi>grant,</hi> which was, that the continuance of this <hi>Parliament</hi> might be limited to the wills of the <hi>Members</hi> thereof, and it not to be dissolved with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the consent of both <hi>Houses:</hi> And although it hath in all Ages been the indisputed right, and indubitate power of the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>England, to Call and Dissolve Parliaments at their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure: Yet His late Majesty, CHARLES the First, of most Glorious and blessed Memory;</hi> willing (if possible) to have satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied His insatiable <hi>People,</hi> granted their request, and ratified his Grant by an <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament:</hi> &amp; now the Sword being put into mad <hi>mens hands,</hi> both <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> having given them up to their own <hi>hearts lusts,</hi> like <hi>bloudy Caniballs</hi> they eagerly pursued their intended <hi>Spoile,</hi> laying the foundation of their cursed <hi>refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:165093:11"/>in the <hi>Innocent Bloud of the Earl of Strafford,</hi> thereby <hi>robbing His Majesty</hi> of a <hi>most faithfull and Loyall Subject,</hi> and the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> of a <hi>most grave and carefull Patriot;</hi> and as they began to lay their foundation <hi>in Bloud</hi> and <hi>Wickednesse,</hi> so they have still continued their Building: and to shew how large a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gresse they were resolved to make into the paths of <hi>Impiety,</hi> they forced His <hi>Majesty</hi> (now with God) to passe an <hi>Act</hi> for the <hi>perpetuall excluding Bishops</hi> from having any Votes <hi>in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> thereby robbing the <hi>Bishops,</hi> those <hi>holy Fathers, of their Ancient and indubitate Right,</hi> and not enduring <hi>God</hi> to have any portion among them. <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1642. they raised an <hi>Army</hi> against <hi>King CHARLES the First,</hi> under the Command of <hi>Robert Earl of Essex and Ewe,</hi> of ignominious and loathed me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, which <hi>Army</hi> proceeded to many great and <hi>Bloudy Battels against that Kings own Person, Children and Subjects. Anno Dom.</hi> 1643. they caused two Innocent <hi>Gentlemen, Mr. Tompkins, and Mr. Challoner</hi> to be <hi>Murdered,</hi> for no other cause but their <hi>Loyalty to their Soveraigne;</hi> and for the same cause they <hi>Impriso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, Sequestred,</hi> and <hi>Plundred</hi> all His <hi>Majesties Loyall Subjects within their Quarters, to their utter Ruine and Destruction. Anno Dom.</hi> 1644. they <hi>Murdered</hi> that most blessed <hi>Martyr</hi> of <hi>ever Glorious Memory, William Land, late Lord Arch-bishop of Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> for no other cause but his <hi>Zeal,</hi> for the <hi>maintenance of the true Protestant Religion in the purity thereof,</hi> as it is Established by the <hi>Law</hi> of this <hi>Land,</hi> and hath continued since the blessed <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> in <hi>Queen Elizabeths dayes,</hi> according to the 39. <hi>Articles,</hi> and his faithfull endeavour to preserve a decent uniformity of <hi>Publique Service</hi> in the <hi>Church.</hi> And that their wicked and <hi>Trayterous Designe</hi> might not <hi>fall,</hi> they <hi>Silenced, Sequestred,</hi> and <hi>Imprisoned</hi> all the <hi>Honest, Pious,</hi> and <hi>Learned Clergy</hi> of the <hi>Land,</hi> and <hi>placed</hi> in their <hi>roomes</hi> a <hi>Peevish, Ignorant,</hi> and <hi>Factious Clergie,</hi> who preached nothing but <hi>Rebellion</hi> and <hi>Sedition.</hi> And for the further maintenance of this their most <hi>horrible</hi> and <hi>unparallelled Rebellion,</hi> they have continually imposed, to the extream grief of the <hi>Subject,</hi> the <hi>Excise, Meal-money, fitfth</hi> and <hi>twentieth part,</hi> and many other insupportable Taxes and Burdens which our fore-fathers <hi>never heard of,</hi> and much beyond all the <hi>Taxes, Subsidies</hi> and <hi>Loanes</hi> that ever were <hi>pay'd</hi> by our <hi>Ancestours</hi> to all
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:165093:12"/>the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>England</hi> since the <hi>Norman Conquest:</hi> so dear a rate have the <hi>mad</hi> and <hi>giddy people</hi> of <hi>England</hi> pay'd for their intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Slavery:</hi> and beyond all this, our great <hi>Task-masters</hi> have subverted <hi>Religior, robbed</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> of its <hi>Patrimony, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thousands</hi> of His <hi>Majesties good Subjects,</hi> countenanced and maintained <hi>Schismes, Heresies, Blasphemies,</hi> both against the <hi>Lord,</hi> and his <hi>Anointed; Sacriledge, Rebellion, Murder, Perjury, Theft, Oppression, Tyranny,</hi> and <hi>thousands</hi> of other most execrable <hi>enormities,</hi> the fourth part whereof would fill a <hi>volume.</hi> And I would to <hi>God</hi> I could have <hi>ended here,</hi> but I must goe yet further, for after they had prosecuted their <hi>Bloudy Warres,</hi> and gotten His late <hi>Majesty</hi> into their <hi>hands,</hi> contrary to all their <hi>solemne Oathes, Covenants, Protestations</hi> and <hi>Declarations,</hi> their engines of deceit, and <hi>Rebellion,</hi> instead of making Him a great and <hi>glorious King,</hi> they made Him a <hi>vile</hi> and <hi>despicable Prisoner, hurrying Him about from one prison to another, and instead of setling Him in His Throne with Glory and Honour, with scorne and contempt the perfidious Jewes brought their King and Saviour to the Crosse instead of the Crowne, they bring His Majesty to the Scaffold, the bed of Death, putting Him to death as a Malefactour, who was a King, most Religious in His profession, most innocent from wrong, and clear in His Conscience from doing the least injury to the worst of His Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects: Ʋpon the Stage (the Scaffold) on the</hi> 30. <hi>of January,</hi> Anno Dom. 1648. <hi>they acted a most fearfull and bloudy Tragedy upon the Person of King CHARLES the First, their Soveraigne Lord; after they had passed the faith of the Kingdome, and given the secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Houses for His security during their Treaty with Him; wherein of His benigne goodnesse, He had granted them such free Concessions of grace and favour, such, and so many, as were never given, not onely by all the Kings of</hi> England, <hi>but by all the Kings of the world in all Ages thereof:</hi> nor were so much as thought of, or desired by the most haughty or audacious People. Thus care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesly did they throw away the blessing of such a <hi>King, of such ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, delectable, and unimaginable endowments, as no Age or Kingdom of the world ever enjoyed.</hi> And after all this can we hope to be free from <hi>Judgements?</hi> no, here is <hi>Judgement</hi> enough if we were <hi>plagued</hi> with no more, to be bereft of such a <hi>King,</hi> but to bereave our selves of such a <hi>King,</hi> is an exalcation of that. But if
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:165093:12"/>we will open our <hi>eyes,</hi> and not be wilfully <hi>blinde,</hi> we may see <hi>Judgements thick and three-fold follow the Actors of this Rebellion:</hi> The <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> who were the first fomenters thereof, who once made honest men <hi>Malignants</hi> to them, are now made <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants</hi> to worse <hi>Rebels</hi> themselves; the <hi>Lords,</hi> who were once so forward to Vote <hi>Bishops</hi> out of their <hi>House,</hi> are now thrown out of their <hi>House</hi> by their <hi>Companions in Rebellion,</hi> and said aside as unusefull <hi>Members,</hi> having been hither to made use on but as <hi>Close-stooles</hi> for the necessity, and <hi>pandours</hi> to the <hi>lusts</hi> of the <hi>Common-people.</hi> Those <hi>Members</hi> that at first were so <hi>active</hi> in the <hi>cause,</hi> and were lookt upon as the <hi>Glorious workers</hi> of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Pillars of the Common-wealth, and Fathers of their <hi>Country;</hi> are now droven out of the <hi>verge</hi> of the <hi>House,</hi> and throwne away as <hi>Rotten Members; Waller, Massey, Browne,</hi> and others the great <hi>Champions</hi> of <hi>Reformation,</hi> are now lookt upon as <hi>Enemies</hi> to the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> byassed men, <hi>Imprisoned,</hi> and to be proceeded against as <hi>Traytours; Essex</hi> their <hi>magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Herod,</hi> was at best but carryed to his <hi>Grave</hi> with a few <hi>Complements,</hi> where he lies <hi>forgotten,</hi> scarce worth an <hi>Epitaph;</hi> The <hi>Hathams</hi> received the reward of their <hi>Rebellion</hi> upon <hi>Tower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill</hi> from the hands of their fellow <hi>Traytors;</hi> the <hi>Covenant,</hi> the <hi>stalking-horse of Rebellion,</hi> is cast into the <hi>fire</hi> as an <hi>Almanack</hi> out of <hi>Date:</hi> The new modelled <hi>Assembly</hi> with their <hi>Calvinian Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites,</hi> those bawling <hi>Rabshekaes,</hi> who stretch their Consciences upon the centers of HILL, breathing from their <hi>Pulpits bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sphemy</hi> against <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Anointed, roaring Rebellion, Bloud and Sedition,</hi> and possessing the <hi>People</hi> with <hi>spirits of madnesse;</hi> now are look'd upon with <hi>envy</hi> and <hi>contempt,</hi> as those <hi>Caterpillars</hi> and <hi>Locusts,</hi> that devoure not onely the <hi>substance, but the Soules of the People: The City, that Parliament-prop, the Refuge and Sanctuary of them, and their Adherents, the Grand Artillery, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazine of confiding men, the Inne and Hospitall of all their maimed Souldiers, and the common Purse and Exchequer together, and heape up money for their Service,</hi> now is look'd upon as the onely <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mora</hi> to <hi>Reformation,</hi> a <hi>dis-affected place,</hi> and filled with their Enemies: that <hi>Army</hi> which they raised, and sent into the bowels of the <hi>Kingdome</hi> for the destruction of <hi>Monarchy,</hi> is now crept into their own <hi>entralls,</hi> threatning and reputing their ruine and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:165093:13"/>
               <hi>devastation,</hi> the onely warrant of their <hi>security:</hi> That <hi>City</hi> which could not live contentedly under the prosperous <hi>Government</hi> of <hi>Kings,</hi> who gave them their <hi>Charter, must live patiently in Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very and Bondage to those Tyrants that will take it from them, and levell their freedome and immunities to a miserable community.</hi> Nor must any of the Authors or Cherishers of this <hi>Rebellion</hi> expect to have their <hi>punishments end here:</hi> For as they walked in untrodden paths of <hi>Rebellion,</hi> so they must expect to be <hi>plagued</hi> with <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Judgements:</hi> Nor must the present <hi>Tragedians</hi> think to go <hi>free,</hi> for as they have acted a more <hi>Bloudy sceane,</hi> so must they expect to <hi>drink deeper</hi> of the <hi>Cup</hi> of more dire <hi>revenge,</hi> for <hi>God</hi> is just, and will not suffer <hi>Bloud, especially Royall Bloud to goe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>revenged,</hi> but will assuredly make strict inquisition for the <hi>Bloud</hi> of the <hi>King,</hi> of <hi>Strafford, Canterbury, Hamilton, Holland, Capell, Lucas, Lisle, and thousands of others, that have already, or shall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after be Murdred by these Bloudy Caniballs.</hi> For undoubtedly the <hi>Bloud</hi> of <hi>Innocents,</hi> the <hi>Bloud</hi> of <hi>Martyrs,</hi> the <hi>Teares</hi> of <hi>Widdowes, Orphans,</hi> and <hi>Oppressed men</hi> and <hi>Women,</hi> now ready to starve through their meanes, have filled <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> with <hi>cryes</hi> for <hi>Vengeance.</hi> And no doubt but the just <hi>God</hi> to whom <hi>Vengeance belongs,</hi> will in his good time shew himselfe in <hi>Vengeance, hurling</hi> it down upon their <hi>Heads,</hi> and pouring forth the full <hi>Vyalls</hi> of his <hi>Indignation</hi> upon these <hi>Disturbers</hi> of this <hi>poor Kingdomes Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>God in his mercy settle King</hi> CHARLES <hi>the Second in Peace, and either speedily convert, or confound his Enemies; to which, let all Loyall hearted English-men say</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>